For a map to render you need at minimum 3 things: 

Map (object):
    -VIEW 
        defines the area where the map will initially be displayed. accepts arguments such as zoom levels there are diff zoom options like min/max. defines initial center for the view.
    -LAYERS
        a map image which you would like to see on the map
    -TARGET CONTAINER
        html element to which you attach your map


No view = map CANNOT display its data! it specifies where and how a user will look at the map. defines the geographic center, resolution, and rotation of the map. 

Layer: provides access to source of geospacial data.
    2 types of geospacial data:
        1. Raster data (refers to digital image) can come from satellite images like remote sensing, aerial photography (drones). uses metrics of square areas (pixels, cells, grids). Excellent for visualization of continuious data. Data which changes continuiously from location to location such as elevation, temperature, etc.
        2. Vector data refers to geometric shapes such as points, lines, and polygons. To represent a vector layer, X and Y coordinates are used, which also defines locations and shapes. Vector data is excellent for visualization of boundaries.

Subclasses of Layer class:

    BaseImageLayer

    BaseTileLayer
        TileLayer:
            used for visualization of raster data

    BaseVectorLayer
        subclasses can be used to visualize vector data in openlayers
            VectorImageLayer
            VectorTileLayer
            VectorLayer
            Heatmap

Overlay: visualization of geospatial data at specific locations on the map. To do that, HTML elements are used. The most common way of using an overlay is to display some info on a pop up. For instance, when a user clicks on the marker or the points on the map, there will be a pop up to show some additional information. 